像大多数人一样，我从像LostinSpace这样的机器人图像中长大，
Like most people I’ve grown up with images of robots like this one from Lost in Space,
但真正的机器人不是这样的。真正的机器人和我们将要看到的机器人
but real robots are not like this. The real robots and the ones we are going to see in
接下来的几分钟，形式和功能都有很大差异。我们要看
the next few minutes have got a great diversity of form and function. We are going to see
可以穿过走廊的机器人，我们将会看到可以游泳的机器人
robots that can move through corridors, we are going to see robots that can swim under
水，可以飞行的机器人，可以组装工作的机器人。它们看起来都很不一样
water, robots that can fly, robots that can do assembly work. They all look very different
它们就像我们在电视和电影中长大的机器人一样。
and they are nothing like the robots that we have grown up with on TV and in the movies.
所有这些机器人的共同点虽然不同，但共同的特点是
What’s common to all these robots although they are different, the common feature is
他们从根本上执行三项行动。他们感知世界，我们将会看到
that they perform fundamentally three actions. They sense the world and we are going to look
在机器人用来感知世界的各种传感器上然后他们做出一些计划，
at a variety of sensors that robots use to sense the world and then they make some plan,
他们通过感官获取他们对世界的看法，并且他们有一个目标
they take what they perceive about the world through their senses and they have got a goal
他们正在努力实现这一目标。所以他们计划如何更接近目标。
that they are trying to achieve. So they plan on how to move a bit closer towards the goal.
然后他们执行一个动作。可能是向前游泳，也可能是飞行，它
And then they perform an action. It might be to swim forward, it might be to fly, it
可能是走下走廊。然后它重复;它再次感觉世界是怎样的
might be to move down the corridor. And then it repeats; it senses again how the world’s
改变了，它更新了计划并进行了更多操作。因此机器人不断进行感应
changed, it updates its plan and moves some more. So robots are continually doing sensing
规划和连续循环。那么我们来看看一些真正的机器人吧。
planning and acting in a continuous loop. So let’s go and look at some real robots.
这是工业机器人的一个例子。
This is an example of an industrial robot.
像这样的机器是直接的后代
Machines like this are direct descendants
在1950年代投入使用的第一批机器人。这是一个非常大的工业
of the first robots that went into service in the 1950's. This is a very big industrial
机器人。像这样的机器人通常会在汽车工厂找到像喷雾这样的工作
robot. Robots like these you will typically find in a car factory doing jobs like spray
汽车车身的涂漆，焊接或提升部件。这个特殊的机器人可以举起
painting, welding, or lifting parts of car bodies. This particular robot can lift up
到60公斤。它由6个电动机驱动，它们使机器绕不同的方向旋转
to 60kgs. It's driven by 6 electric motors and they rotate the machine around different
轴。因此，第一个电机围绕这样的轴旋转机器人;下一个电机旋转
axes. So, the first motor rotates the robot about an axis like this; the next motor rotates
关于像这样的轴;下一个电机围绕这样的轴旋转。我们在这里
it about an axis like this; next motor rotates it about an axis like this. Down here we have
我们称之为腕部机制。这个组装在这里;那包含三个电机和它们
what we call the wrist mechanism. This assembly here; and that contains three motors and they
旋转机器人的末端执行器;做这项工作的那一点;他们旋转它
rotate the end effector of the robot; the bit that does the work; they rotate it about
像这样的轴，像这样，另一个像这样。所以这六个电机允许结束
an axis like this, like this and another one like this. So these six motors allow the end
机器人的效应器在X方向，Y方向和X方向上独立移动
effector of the robot to move independently in the X direction, the Y direction and the
Z方向。并且也像这样独立地围绕X轴旋转;关于Y轴
Z direction. And also to rotate independently about the X axis like that; about the Y axis
就是这样的动作;并且关于像这样的运动的Z轴。
which is motion like that; and about the Z axis which is motion like that.
这是Guiabot。这是一个移动机器人。不像我们看到的最后一个机器人
This is the Guiabot. This is a mobile robot. Unlike the last robot that we looked at this
机器人能够在环境中自动移动。要使它能够做到
robot has the ability to autonomously move through an environment. To enable it to do
它拥有丰富的传感器。这个传感器对你来说可能很熟悉
that, it has a rich collection of sensors. This sensor is probably familiar to you, it’s
一个Kinect相机。我们称之为3D相机。它输出三维结构
a Kinect camera. We call it a 3D camera. It outputs the three dimensional structure of
机器人周围的世界。它需要三维结构才能实现
the world around the robot. And it needs that three dimensional structure so that it can
确定什么是障碍-它不应该驱动的地方-以及什么是自由空间
determine what's an obstacle - a place that it shouldn't drive - and what's free space
-这是可以开车的空间。机器人也有这对
– that’s space where it is okay for it to drive. The robot also has got this pair
这里的相机，我们称之为立体相机对，它模仿我们自己的功能
of cameras here, we call this a stereo camera pair, and it mimics the function of our own
两只眼睛。我们用两只眼睛来确定世界的3D结构。所以机器人
two eyes. We use our two eyes to determine the 3D structure of the world. So the robot
使用它来提供有关其世界的增强3D信息。机器人也得到了
uses this to provide augmented 3D information about its world. The robot’s also got a
顶部非常有趣的相机。我们称之为全方位相机。实际上
very interesting camera on the top. We call this an omnidirectional camera. It's actually
由六个单独的摄像头组成，这些摄像头也可以看到所有这些不同的方向
made up of six individual cameras which look in all these different directions as well
垂直的它将它们整合在一起，几乎呈现出半球形的视角
as vertically. It integrates that together to give almost a hemispherical view of the
世界。一个非常非常广角的视图。
world. A very, very wide angle view.
这个机器人的其他功能也很有趣。在这里，我们有一个传感器，我们称之为
Other features of this robot are also interesting. Down here we have a sensor that we call a
激光扫描仪。这基本上是一个光学保险杠。它是最后的传感器
laser scanner. This is essentially an optical bumper bar. It is the sensor of last resort
阻止机器人撞到不应撞到的东西。机器人也有
to stop the robot bumping into something that it shouldn't bump into. The robot has also
掌上了很多计算能力。我们在这里看到我们还有两台MacMinis
got a lot of computing power onboard. We see here we have got two Mac Minis in addition
到基础中的计算机并提供处理的计算能力
to a computer which is in the base and that provides the computational power to process
来自所有传感器的信息，以计划它应该如何移动和控制运动
the information from all the sensors to plan how it should move and to control the motion
的轮子。这个机器人对它的位置有很强的感觉;它实际上建立起来了
of the wheels. This robot has got a very strong sense of where it is; it actually builds up
它的世界地图;二维和三维地图。它知道它在哪里
a map of its world; a two dimensional and a 3 dimensional map. It knows where it is
在这个世界中，它需要的基本信息才能实现
within that world and the fundamental information it needs in order to be able to achieve a
目标。所以它可以感觉到，它在这里规划计算机并将动作发送到
goal. So it can sense, it's got planning computers here and that sends actions through to the
电机和它不断重复这种传感，规划，行动范式。
motors and it continually repeats this sensing, planning, acting paradigm.
在这里，我们有另一个移动机器人，这是一个巨大的。像这样的机器被称为
Here we have another mobile robot and this is a giant one. Machines like these are called
热金属载体。他们是叉车的亲戚。他们通常被发现
hot metal carriers. They are a relative of the forklift truck. They are typically found
在铝冶炼设施和他们的工作是拿起非常大的水桶像
in aluminium smelting facilities and their job is to pick up very large buckets like
这个你可以在前景中看到这里将填充熔融铝
this one you can see in the foreground here which will be filled with molten aluminium
-8吨熔铝。他们的工作是拿起这个水桶，抬起它并随身携带
- 8 tonnes of molten aluminium. Their job is to pick up this bucket, lift it and carry
它沿着一个公路网络到达这个冶炼综合体内的另一个地方。
it along a road network to another place within this smelting complex.
这台机器最初是由一个坐在驾驶室里操纵的人驾驶的
This machine was originally driven by a person who would sit in a cab here and manipulate
控件，但这台特殊的机器已经变成了一个机器人。为了
the controls, but this particular machine has been turned into a robot. In order for
它是一个有效的机器人，它需要使用许多不同的传感器，以避免它
it to be an effective robot, it needs to use a number of different sensors so that it avoids
击中它不应击中的东西或人，它可以确定它在哪里
hitting things or people that it shouldn't hit, that it can determine where it is within
冶炼厂的复杂，也能够成功地拿起坩埚。
the smelter complex, and also to be able to successfully pick up the crucible.
现在，让我们来看看提货过程。车辆本身就有这个钩子
Now, let's look at the pick up process. The vehicle itself has got this hook which it
需要通过这个句柄输入。所以这是一个相对精确的定位问题
needs to put in through this handle. So it's a relatively precise positioning problem that
机器人需要解决。现在它通过使用一个在这里的相机来做到这一点
the robot needs to solve. Now it does that by using a camera which is up here on the
机器人的桅杆，向下看，并找出这个桶相对于它的位置
mast of the robot, which looks down and works out where this bucket is with respect to the
机器人，机器人移动，以便通过此手柄将此钩子带入。
robot, and the robot moves so as to bring this hook in through this handle.
这个机器人上另一个非常重要的传感器是这个黄色激光扫描设备，和
Another really important sensor on this robot is this yellow laser scanning device, and
实际上有四个，一个在机器人的每个角落，所以它可以看到所有
there’s actually four of them, one on each corner of the robot so that it can see all
绕道而行。这执行两个功能。一个是激光束可以检测到的东西
the way around. This performs two functions. One is the laser beams can detect something
像我一样，一个障碍，它会停止，所以它不会与我发生碰撞。但它也
like me, an obstacle, and it would then stop so it wouldn't collide with me. But it also
执行一项非常重要的导航任务。这就是机器人知道它在哪里的方式
performs a really important navigation task. This is how the robot knows where it is within
复杂的。因此，要了解它是如何工作的，我们将走出去看一个
the complex. So to understand how that works we are going to go outside and look at one
该传感器拾取的导航标记。
of the navigation markers that this sensor picks up.
机器人使用标记系统在环境中工作。在这个特别的
The robot works out where it is in the environment using a system of markers. In this particular
这些反光带条在激光扫描仪上给出了非常明亮的回报
case these strips of reflective tape which give really bright returns on the laser scanners
我们在热金属载体的角落看到的那些黄色装置。现在机器人了
those yellow devices that we saw on the corners of the hot metal carrier. Now the robot has
得到了一张地图，告诉它所有这些标记都位于复合体内。然后呢
got a map that tells it whereabouts all these markers are within the complex. And then it
使用有关机器人感知这些标记的位置的信息，并将其组合在一起
uses the information about where the robot perceives these markers to be and it combines
两者共同确定机器人相对于地图的位置。
both of those together to determine where the robot is with respect to the map.
在这里，我们有另一种移动机器人。这个可以在空中移动。这是一个小的
Here we have another kind of mobile robot. This one is mobile in the air. It's a small
规模直升机-这是业余爱好者所拥有的一种东西。有点像他们的东西
scale helicopter - it's a sort of thing that a hobbyist would own. Sort of thing that they
可能会在周末飞行，他们使用操纵杆控制飞行它需要相当多
might fly on the weekend and they fly it using joystick controls that requires quite a lot
他们的技能，以保持在空中，并去他们想要的地方。
of skill on their part in order to keep it in the air and go where they want it to go.
这台特殊的机器已经转换成机器人，但在我们谈论之前
This particular machine has been converted into a robot but before we talk about the
机器人部分，让我们谈谈直升机机器本身，因为
robotic part, let’s just talk a little bit about the helicopter machine itself because
它们是令人着迷的东西。
they are fascinating things.
这是由一个小型汽油发动机提供动力;这里有一个燃料箱
This is powered by a small petrol engine; there is a fuel tank down here that carries
燃料。主升力来自提供力矢量的主转子
the fuel. And the main lift force comes from the main rotor that provides a force vector
垂直向上，抵消车辆的重量-抵消重力。
vertically upwards, which counteracts the weight of the vehicle - counteracts gravity.
直升机的惊人之处在于它可以将力矢量指向不同的方向。
The amazing thing with the helicopter is it can point the force vector in different directions.
它可以指向前方，它可以指向它，它可以指向侧面，这一切都已完成
It can point it forward, it can point it backwards, it can point it sideways and that's all done
通过这种机制，这里称为旋转斜盘，每次刀片都是这样做的
by this mechanism here called the swash plate and what that does is every time the blades
旋转，它们也围绕它们的轴旋转，以便允许这个力矢量
rotate, they also rotate this way about their axis so that allows this force vector to be
控制并使其具有向前，向后，侧向和悬停的能力。
controlled and that gives it the ability to move forward, backwards, sideways and hover.
在这里的背面还有另一个螺旋桨，它提供了一个阻止整体的力量
There is another propeller on the back here and that provides a force to stop the whole
直升机的身体旋转。
body of the helicopter rotating around.
为了将其变成机器人，我们需要为它添加一些传感器。所以在这个盒子里
In order to turn it into a robot, we need to add some sensors to it. So in this box
在这里，有一些传感器，如GPS，它告诉它在哪里尊重
down here, there are some sensors such as GPS which tells it where it is with respect
致全世界。有一些加速度计和陀螺仪可以告诉它它的方向
to the world. There are some accelerometers and gyroscopes that tell it its orientation
在太空。这里有一个激光高度计，它可以告诉它高于地面的高度
in space. There is a laser altimeter here which tells it its height above the ground
在前面是一个雷达探测它可能飞入的障碍物。
and in the front is a radar which detects obstacles that it might fly into.
因此，像这样的机器人直升机对于许多类型的任务都很有用。它对自动检测很有用：
So, a robotic helicopter like this is useful for many kinds of tasks. It's useful for automated inspection:
也许在农场，它可以检查作物的质量，它可以沿着小溪和水道飞行，
perhaps on a farm it could inspect the quality of crops, it could fly along creeks and waterways,
它可以沿着电线或沿着栅栏线飞行。
it could fly along electricity lines or along fence lines.
在这里我们有另一种类型的移动机器人，但这个机器人可以通过水移动。
Here we have another type of mobile robot but this robot is mobile through water.
我们使用这样的机器人对湖泊等大量水进行科学测量
We use robots like this to make scientific measurements about large volumes of water like lakes
或沿海地区。它看起来很简单，但实际上是一个非常复杂和复杂的机器。
or coastal zones. It looks quite simple but is actually quite a complex and sophisticated machine.
让我们来看看吧。在这一端，我们有一个螺旋桨推动
Let’s walk through it. Down at this end we have a propeller that pushes the
整个机器人穿过水面。它有一些控制鳍，方向舵在这里引导它
whole robot through the water. It's got some control fins, rudder is here to steer it through
水体和这些飞机在这里使它在水柱中上下移动。这个
the water body and these planes here make it move up and down in the water column. This
这里的天线堆栈有一个GPS接收器，所以当它在水面上时就知道了
antenna stack here has got a GPS receiver so when it's on the water surface it knows
在哪里，它有一些其他天线，允许我们与它进行通信
where it is, and it has got some other antennas that allow us to communicate with it when
它出海了。这里我们有声纳传感器-侧扫声纳-它使用声波
it is out at sea. Here we have sonar sensors - side scan sonar - which uses sound waves
当机器人经过时，建立海床的三维地图。上面这儿
to build up a three dimensional map of the sea bed as the robot passes over it. Up here
我们有一些测量海流速度的传感器。即使是机器人
we have some sensors that measure the speed of the ocean current. Even though the robot
正在移动，他们可以测量水柱的速度。在下面还有另一个
is moving, they can measure the speed of the water column. Underneath there is another
传感器测量机器人相对于水柱的速度。在前面
sensor that measures the speed of the robot with respect to the water column. Up the front
这是科学有效载荷，这是我们想要推动的仪器
here is the scientific payload and this is the instrumentation that we want to push through
水可以测量正在发生的事情。所以这里有我们测量的传感器
the water to make measurements about what's going on. So here we have sensors that measure
水的电导率和pH值;测量溶解氧的量;那
the conductivity and pH of the water; that measure the amount of dissolved oxygen; that
测量叶绿素的量;测量蓝绿藻的数量。所以这个科学
measure the amount of chlorophyll; measures the amount of blue green algae. So this scientific
数据与来自其他传感器的导航数据合并
data is merged with navigational data which comes from the other sensors on board the
机器人，所以我们知道这些测量的位置。
robot, so we know where these measurements have been taken.
这个特殊的机器人运行时间长达8小时，每秒移动约2米，
This particular robot has got a runtime of up to 8 hours, moves about 2 meters per second,
所以我们可以一次性测量水中约30公里。
so we can survey about 30 kilometres in water in a single run.
所以我们刚刚看到的是一些非常有趣，令人兴奋和明显有用的东西
So what we have just seen are a number of really interesting, exciting and clearly useful
机器人。这些机器人的形式和功能各不相同，但在这些机器人内部
robots. These robots differ in their form and in their function, but inside these robots
都在做同样的事情。他们正在感知他们的世界，他们正在制定计划
are all doing the same thing. They are sensing their world, they are making plans and then
他们正在为实现目标而采取行动。某些
they are they are carrying out actions in order to achieve their goals. Some of the
我们看到的机器人显然是研究原型，但其他机器人是商业产品。还有这个
robots that we saw were clearly research prototypes, but others were commercial products. And this
真是令人兴奋，因为这是一个全新的技术浪潮的开始，我们有
is really exciting because this is the beginning of a whole new technological wave and we have
在过去见证了许多技术浪潮。引入蒸汽动力，电力，
witnessed many technological waves in the past. The introduction of steam power, electricity,
飞行器，汽车，电力，计算机;所有这些都令人惊讶
flying machines, automobiles, electricity, computers; all these things were surprising
给我们的祖父母和我们的父母。机器人将成为下一个技术
to our grandparents and to our parents. Robots are just going to be the next technological
挥之不去，在不久的将来，我们将在我们的网站上看到它们并不令人惊讶
wave and in the near future, we are going to be quite unsurprised to see them in our
工作场所和我们的家园。所以前方显然非常有趣。
workplaces and in our homes. So there are clearly really interesting times ahead.